Guide to the Jeffrey Gerson Brooklyn politics research collection 2013.021
Brooklyn Historical Society
Jeffrey Gerson Brooklyn politics research collection
1933-1994
1985-1994
Brooklyn Historical Society
Gerson, Jeffrey N.
2013.021
7.48 Linear feet in 5 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, 1 half manuscript box, and 3 shoe boxes.
56.7 Gigabytes in 436 files.
This collection contains materials related to Jeffrey Gerson's interviews in the 1980s and 1990s of Brooklyn-based politicians and community organizers who were active in the 1960s and 1970s. Materials include audio recordings, newspaper clippings, transcripts, and handwritten notes.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title, which reflects the donor's original order.
Biographical Note
Jeffrey Gerson is a professor in the Department of Political Science at University of Massachusetts – Lowell. He graduated from Canarsie High School in 1974 and received his B.A. from the State University of New York Brockport in 1978. During the summer of 1984, Gerson was a research assistant for Sharon Zukin, professor at Brooklyn College, and Gilda Zwerman, professor at State University of New York (SUNY) Westbury.
Gerson received his PhD in political science from the City University of New York Graduate School and University Center. His dissertation was on Irish, Jewish, and Black political succession in Central Brooklyn.
From 1992-1993, Gerson was a Scholar in Residence at the Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture. His research project focused on Black democratic clubhouses in New York City and how they worked with or responded to new state and federal social programs and social movements in the 1960s.
Conditions Governing Access
Physical files are open to users without restriction. Oral histories are only available to listen to onsite in the Othmer Library. The Irene Baker interview is restricted and not available for research use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jeffrey Gerson, 2014.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Cassette tapes in this collection are not available for research use. Corresponding digital surrogates should be used in place of the originals.
Scope and Contents
The Jeffrey Gerson Brooklyn politics research collection is made up of materials related to Jeffrey Gerson's research on Brooklyn politics and interviews of Brooklyn-based political leaders and community leaders active in the 1960s and before.
These research files are titled with the names of organizations, people, authors of papers Gerson consulted, or related subjects. They contain newspaper clippings, research papers, copies of materials found in other archives, and transcripts from oral history projects conducted at other organizations.
74 of these files are related to people that Gerson interviewed. These files may contain a transcript, handwritten notes about the interview, and newspaper clippings. Each interview includes a biography written by Gerson and keywords related to the content of the interview. The interview may also be accompanied by a digital audio file with Gerson's comments on the interview. The Scope and Contents note at the file level of this finding aid will note whether there is an accompanying transcript.
Interviews from 1984 are from Gerson's work as a research assistant for Professors Sharon Zukin and Gilda Zwerman for their article "Housing for the Working Poor: A Historical View of Jews and Blacks in Brownsville" published in New York Affairs in 1985. Interviews from 1985-1989 were conducted for Gerson's dissertation research, which culminated in Building the Brooklyn Machine: Irish, Jewish and Black Political Succession in Central Brooklyn, 1919-1964, published in 1990. Interviews from 1992-1993 were conducted for Gerson's work as a Scholar in Residence at the Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture, a project focused on Black democratic clubhouse politics in New York City.
Related Materials
Center for Brooklyn History holds the following related materials:
- Building the Brooklyn machine: Irish, Jewish, and black political succession in Central Brooklyn, 1919-1964, 1990 (JF2101 .G47)
- Joseph R. Lentol papers (CBHM.0004)
- Brian Purnell Civil Rights in Brooklyn Oral History collection (BCMS.0012)
- Arnie Goldwag Brooklyn Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) collection (ARC.002)
- Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation oral histories (2008.030)
- Alan Maisel and Bernard Catcher collection on Brooklyn politics (2016.001)
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Archives holds the Simon W. and Sophie Gerson Papers (TAM.330).
The Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture holds the Thomas Russell Jones papers (Sc MG 818).
Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Politics and government; Oral histories (document genres); African Americans -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Newspaper clippings; Politicians -- New York (State); Irish Americans -- Political activity -- New York (State); Jews -- Politics and government; African Americans -- Relations with Jews; Transcripts; Communists; Democratic Party (Kings County, N.Y.); Republican Party (Kings County, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Gerson, Jeffrey N.; Ablack, Antoinette, 1908-1991; Bailey, Lawrence R., 1918-1998; Baker, Irene L., 1901-2001; Beame, Abraham D. (Abraham David); Berman, Samuel I., 1911-1991; Bernstein, Charles E., 1901-1991; Blyn, Arthur E., 1911-2005; Bramwell, Arthur, 1918-2003; Bravo, Josephine M., -2010; Brooks, Ruth, 1925-2006; Carney, Vincent P.; Carter, Patrick; Chisholm, William M., 1912-1998; Cooper, Andrew W., 1927-2002; Crichlow, Ernest, 1914-2005; Dubin, Marshall F. (Marshall Frank), 1918-2004; Easton, Richard J., 1934-; Esquirol, Joseph A., Jr., 1932-2015; Feiden, Murray T.; Fisher, Harold L. (Harold Leonard), 1910-1999; Frank, Sylvia, 1921-; Frett-Moses, Narcissus, 1929-2022; Garry, William J., 1929-2009; Gerson, Simon W.; Goldner, Milton, 1926-2002; Goldwag, Arnold; Goring, Ruth G., 1919-2006; Hayes, John F., 1915-; Heller, Louis B., 1905-1993; Hesterberg, Gregory X.; Holder, Wesley McDonald, 1897-1993; Jacobs, Harold, 1912-1995; Jones, Thomas R. (Thomas Russell), 1913-2006; Jordan, Anthony T., Jr., 1924-1995; Keogh, Eugene, 1907-1989; Kessler, Joseph, 1919-1996; Lentol, Joseph R., 1943-; Leone, Sebastian; Linder, Walter, 1930-2022; Lupka, Herbert, -2018; Mangano, James V., 1905-1988; Maynard, Joan; McLaughlin, Harold J., 1905-1993; Morton, Franklin W., Jr., 1920-2014; Murray, Albert R., 1921-2005; Nelson, Leon, 1915-1995; O'Dwyer, Paul, 1907-1998; Orlando, Joseph J., 1904-1992; Orr, Dorothy James, 1920-2015; Pankey, Hulett S., 1903-1991; Pierce, Lawrence W. (Lawrence Warren), 1924-2020; Rosenberg, J. Mitchell, 1906-2000; Rosenberg, Murray, 1925-2003; Ryan, Herbert F., 1931-2022; Scholnick, Leonard; Scott, Josephine, 1921-2006; Sharkey, Joseph T., 1893-1991; Shaw, James, 1923-; Sheppard, Daphne A., 1917-2006; Sherwood, Charles L., 1900-2000; Sipser, I. Philip, 1918-; Sobel, Nathan R., 1906-1997; Squire, Sidney, 1906-1997; Steingut, Stanley; Strelzin, Harvey N., 1906-1993; Taylor, Gardner C.; Vann, Albert; Weusi, Jitu, 1939-2013; Williams, Everett, 1905-2001; Woods, Mary Elizabeth, 1930-2005; Wright, Samuel D., 1925-1998; Yagerman, Lila, 1928-1997
- Antoinette Ablack "Tony", 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1, Box 8, Cassette 1)
  Biographical Note
  Antoinette "Tony" Ablack was born August 11, 1908 in the Bronx, New York. Ablack was a long-time member of Vincent P. Carney's 17th Assembly District Democratic Club in Brooklyn. Ablack died in February 1991.
  Scope and Contents
  This interview was conducted on September 15, 1989 in Lone Eddy, New York. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Cassette tapes are not available for research use. Access to the interview is available digitally onsite at Center for Brooklyn History's Othmer Library.
  One original audiocassette.
  Three preservation .WAV files. One access .mp3 file.
- Charles Abrams, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Anti-poverty clippings, 1966-1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Lawrence Bailey, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 4, Box 8, Cassette 2, Cassette 3)
  Lawrence R. Bailey, Sr. was born on March 18, 1918 in the Panama Canal Zone. Bailey received a bachelor's degree and law degree from Howard University in Washington, DC. In 1970, Bailey was appointed to the board of the Metropolitan Transit Authority and was the first Black member and officer to serve on that board. Bailey also had a private law practice based in Harlem and served as President of the Harlem Lawyers Association. He died in April 1998.
  The interview was conducted on June 10, 1993 at Bailey's law office in Harlem, Manhattan. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
  Two original audio cassettes.
- Bertram Baker, circa 1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Bertram Baker, 1956-1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Bertram Baker, 1958-1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Bertram Baker clippings, 1943-1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Irene Baker, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 9, Box 8, Cassette 4, Cassette 5, Cassette 6)
  Irene L. Baker was born on March 24, 1901 in Brooklyn, New York. Baker's parents are from Nevis in the West Indies. Growing up, Baker's family lived in Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn Heights, and East New York. She married her cousin Bertram L. Baker on December 10, 1919. In 1948, Bertram L. Baker was elected to the New York State Assembly and was the first Black person elected to political office by voters in Brooklyn. Irene L. Baker was involved in political organizing, collecting signatures for petitions to get Democratic party candidates on the ballot in Bedford-Stuyvesant. Irene L. Baker died in January of 2001.
  This interview took place on July 12, 1989 at Irene L. Baker's home in Bedford-Stuyvesant. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
  Cassette tapes are not available for research use.
  Three preservation .WAV files. Three access .mp3 files.
  Conditions Governing Access
  This interview is restricted and not available for research use.
- Abraham Beame, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 10, Box 8, Cassette 7, Cassette 8)
  Abraham Beame was born on March 20, 1906 in London, England and grew up on the Lower East Side of Manhattan. His Polish-Jewish parents fled Warsaw, Poland and changed their name from Birnbaum to Beame when arriving in the United States. He attended P.S. 160 and Commerce High School. He married Mary Ingerman in 1928 and they moved to Brooklyn, living in Crown Heights with their two sons and later near Prospect Park. Beame owned a certified public accounting firm and taught accounting classes. Abraham and Mary were both members of the Madison Democratic Club, run by Irwin Steingut, in Crown Heights. He was first elected to office as city comptroller in 1961 and then was mayor from 1974 to 1977, during the height of the city's fiscal crisis. He ran again in 1977, but lost in the Democratic primary. He died on February 10, 2001.
  This interview took place on November 27, 1985 at Bank Leumi offices in Manhattan. The audio from this interview includes audio comments from Jeffrey Gerson after the interview. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
  Two preservation .WAV files. Two access .mp3 files.
  Gerson's audio comments are on one preservation .WAV file and one access .mp3 file.
- Bedford-Stuyvesant, 1960-1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Monroe Berliner, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Samuel Berman, 1986-1991 (Box 1, Folder 13, Box 8, Cassette 9, Cassette 10, Box 10, Cassette 24)
  Samuel Berman was born on January 19, 1911 in Manhattan and grew up in Bedford-Stuyvesant. His parents were born in Russia and fled from the Cossacks to the United States. He served as New York State Assemblyman from 1954 to 1962. Before serving as New York State Assemblyman, he was Executive Director of the City Council's Committee on Reapportionment and Secretary to New York City's Department of Markets. After his terms in the NYS Assembly, Berman served as Deputy Commissioner of Public Works in New York City. In 1967, he was appointed to the New York State Lottery Commission. He retired in 1974 and died in April 1991.
  Samuel Berman was interviewed twice, once on January 22, 1986 and once on March 12, 1986, at his apartment in Midwood. Neither of these interviews are accompanied by a transcript.
  Three original audio cassettes.
  Five preservation .WAV files. Five access .mp3 files.
- Charles Bernstein, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 14, Box 8, Cassette 10)
  Charles E. Bernstein was born in Westchester County on June 22, 1901 and grew up in the Brownsville neighborhood of Brooklyn. He was involved with the Madison Democratic Club and served as a captain in the 2nd Assembly District Club. His son, Aaron D. Bernstein, was a Brooklyn Supreme Court Justice. Charles Bernstein died April 3, 1991.
  The interview took place on August 19, 1987 in Judge Aaron Bernstein's Brooklyn Supreme Courthouse chambers. Audio related to this interview includes audio comments from Jeffrey Gerson after the interview. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
  One original audio cassette.
  Jeffrey Gerson's audio comments are on one preservation .WAV file and one access .mp3 file.
- Oscar Bernstein, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Jacob Besunder, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Black politics 1960s clippings, 1965-1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Black politics, late '70s early '80s, 1955-1981 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Black politics and the Vietnam War, 1966-1993 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Black politics and the Vietnam War, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Black politics and the Vietnam War, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Black politics and the Vietnam War, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Black politics and the Vietnam War, 1965-1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Black politics NYC [clippings], 1965 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Black politics NYC clippings, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Arthur Blyn, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 26, Box 8, Cassette 12)
  Arthur E. Blyn was born on August 30, 1911 in Manhattan. Blyn received his undergraduate degree from the University of Rochester and law degree from the New York Law School. Blyn was chairman of the American Labor Party in Brooklyn's 18th Assembly District and then later served as a judge on the Civil Court of the City of New York and the Surrogate and Supreme Courts of New York County. He died on January 8, 2005.
  This interview was conducted on May 12, 1988. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
  One preservation .WAV file. One access .mp3 file.
- William Henry Booth, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Arthur Bramwell, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 28, Box 8, Cassette 13, Cassette 14)
  Arthur Bramwell was born on September 1, 1918 in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York. His parents were from Jamaica. Bramwell started his career in politics by campaigning for Wendell Wilkie's unsuccessful 1940 presidential bid. He stayed active in Kings County republican politics and and served as a delegate to the Republican National Convention several times. Bramwell served as county party chairman for the Brooklyn GOP from 1993 to 2001. Bramwell died on April 8, 2003.
  This interview took place on April 7, 1989. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
- Josephine Bravo, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 29, Box 8, Cassette 12, Box 9, Cassette 51)
  Josephine M. Bravo was a political activist and member of Bertram L. Baker's United Action Democratic Club in Brooklyn and was a New York City school teacher. She died on November 22, 2010 when she was 90 years old.
  The interview took place on May 21, 1988 at Josephine Bravo's home in Baltimore, Maryland. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
- Brooklyn, 1963-1988 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Brooklyn Heights - Fort Greene, circa 1959 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Brooklyn left wing, 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Brooklyn Newsday clippings, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Ruth Brooks, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 34, Box 8, Cassette 15, Box 10, Cassette 1)
  Ruth Brooks was born on December 9, 1925 in Brooklyn, New York. Brooks was a political activist and member of the Unity Democratic Club, founded by Thomas Russell Jones, in Brooklyn. Her father was A. David Benjamin, a Republican and American Labor Party candidate for Civil Court and an Appellate Court Judge in New York. Her grandmother Annie Benjamin wrote some of the Yiddish advice column "A Bintel Brief." Brooks died in 2006.
  This interview took place on May 2, 1988 at Ruth Brooks' home in Brooklyn, New York. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
- Brownsville, 1919-1983 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Canarsie, 1985-1998 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Vincent Carney, 1958-1989 (Box 1, Folder 37, Box 8, Cassette 5, Cassette 16)
  Vincent P. Carney was born on July 6, 1910 in Brooklyn, New York. He was the Assembly District Leader for the 17th Assembly District in Brooklyn after his brother Stephen Carney died in 1953. He was an alternate delegate to the Democratic National Convention from New York in 1956. He died on July 22, 1994.
  The interview took place on June 20, 1989 at Vincent Carney's home in Manhattan. Vincent Carney discusses his brother's relationship with Bertram Baker and his own leadership of the 17th Assembly after his brother Stephen Carney died. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
- Patrick Carter, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 38, Box 8, Cassette 17)
  Patrick Carter was born on March 17, 1924 in the Brownsville neighborhood of Brooklyn. He was a member of the Unity Democratic Club during the late 1950s and early 1960s. He was an insurance consultant in Manhattan. He died in 1994.
  This interview took place on March 27, 1992. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
  One original audio cassettes.
  Two preservation .WAV files. One access .mp3 file.
- John Cashmore, 1940-1989 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Photos - Brooklyn, John Cashmore, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Emanuel Celler, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Central Brooklyn Coordinating Council, Inc., 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Chinese-American Planning Council, Inc., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Shirley Chisholm, 1978-1993 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Shirley Chisholm, 1968-1990 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- William Chisholm, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 46, Box 8, Cassette 18, Cassette 19)
  William Chisholm was born on October 15, 1912 in Savannah, Georgia. He started practicing law in Brooklyn in 1951, working with R. Risley Dent, Jr. and Thaddeus Owens. He worked for the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) and the New York City Fireman's Union. Chisholm was a member of the Brooklyn-Long Island Alumni Chapter of Kappa Alpha Psi. He died on August 8, 1998.
  This interview took place on May 7, 1993. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
- Vivian Cook, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Andrew Cooper, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 48, Box 8, Cassette 20)
  Andrew W. Cooper was born on August 21, 1927 in the Clinton Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn. He was a political activist and early member of the Unity Democratic Club. Cooper was an executive of the F. + M. Schaefer Brewing Company from 1951 to 1971 and then became a journalist, writing a column for The Amsterdam News and contributing to The Village Voice. In 1984, Cooper founded The City Sun, which folded in 1996 due to financial issues. Cooper was married to Jocelyn Cooper. He died on January 28, 2002.
  This interview took place on April 13, 1988 in Andrew Cooper's office at the City Sun in Brooklyn. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
- Jocelyn Cooper, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 49, Box 8, Cassette 21)
  Jocelyn E. Cooper was born on January 27, 1929 in Jersey City, New Jersey. She was a social worker and early member of the Unity Democratic Club. She was married to Andrew W. Cooper.
  This interview took place on February 17, 1988 at Jocelyn Cooper's home in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
- Congress on Racial Equality (CORE), 1962-1989 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Congress on Racial Equality (CORE), 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Michael Jones Correa, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Ernest Crichlow, circa 1987 (Box 2, Folder 3, Box 8, Cassette 22)
  Ernest Crichlow was born on June 19, 1914 in Brooklyn, New York. His parents had immigrated from Barbados. He studied commercial art in Manhattan and worked for the Works Progress Administration federal arts program during the Depression. He was active in the Unity Democratic Club during the late 1950s and early 1960s. In 1958, he helped found the Fulton Art Fair in Brooklyn and in 1969, he co-founded the Cinque Gallery in Manhattan with Romare Bearden and Norman Lewis. He died on November 10, 2005.
  This interview took place on September 25, 1989 at Ernest Crichlow's home in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
- Crown Heights, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Irwin Davidson, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- J. Daniel Diggs, circa 1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- David Dinkins, 1990-1993 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Amy C. Dombeck, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  This file contains a student paper by Amy C. Dombeck titled "The Women's Suffrage Movement and its Impact on the Political Parties from 1910-1920."
- Joe Dorinson, Prof. History, LIU [Long Island University], 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Marshall [and Etheline] Dubin, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 10, Box 8, Cassette 23)
  This interview took place on February 17, 1988. Etheline Dubin, Marshall F. Dubin's wife, also joins for part of the interview. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
  Marshall Frank Dubin, PhD was born on October 10, 1918 in Chicago, Illinois. He moved to New York City in 1947 and married Etheline Dunbar in 1955. He was a political activist and involved in the American Labor Party and Fair Employment Practices Commission (FEPC) in New York City. He was also a member of the Unity Democratic Club. He died January 29, 2004.
  Etheline Dubin was born Etheline Dunbar in 1925 in Boston, Massachusetts. She was a social worker and community activist, and also a member of the Unity Democratic Club. She married Marshall F. Dubin in 1955. Etheline Dubin died on September 18, 1997.
- James Dumpson, 1960-1993 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Anthony Durso, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- East New York, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Richard Easton, 1966-1993 (Box 2, Folder 14, Box 8, Cassette 24, Cassette 25)
  Richard J. Easton was born on July 30, 1934 in Chicago, Illinois. He was a political activist in Brooklyn during the 1960s and 1970s. He was active in the American Teachers Association (later merged to be the National Education Association). He was Deputy Superintendent for New York City schools in the Inwood area.
  This interview took place on July 14, 1993 at Richard Easton's home on Roosevelt Island. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
- Emergency Medical Services New York City 1980s (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Emergency Medical Services New York City 1980s, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 16 - 17)
- Meade Esposito, 1988-1993 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Joseph A. Esquirol, Jr., 1987 (Box 2, Folder 19 - 21, Box 8, Cassette 26, Cassette 27, Cassette 28, Box 9, Cassette 1)
  Joseph A. Esquirol, Jr. was born on September 29, 1932. His parents were State Senator Joseph A. Esquirol and Louise Downs Esquirol. He grew up in the Flatbush neighborhood of Brooklyn and went to the Berkshire School, Trinity College, and New York Law School, graduating in 1959. He worked for the New York City Corporation Counsel and then the New York City Housing Court. In 1977, he became a Kings County family court judge. Judge Esquirol retired in 1991 and moved to Mattituck, Long Island. He died April 13, 2015.
  This interview took place on August 2, 1987 at Joseph A. Esquirol's summer home in the Hamptons on Long Island. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
  Five original audio cassettes.